It’s crazy when you think about all of
the different kinds of foods we eat.
We just swallow and hope
it all works out for the best.
Well, as it turns out,
there are better ways to think about keeping
our bodies humming healthfully along.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast,
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
In this episode,
Dr. Kristine Dennis continues
a deep dive into the research
around raising
plant based kids.
Dr. Dennis is our new
Senior Research Scientist
who also happens to
be a plant-based parent.
Today, Dr. Dennis asks
how can we plan well-balanced plant-
based diets for infants and kids?
The American Academy
of Nutrition and Dietetics
considers plant-based diets
suitable for pregnancy,
as well as during lactation,
infancy, and childhood,
when they are well-planned.
So, what goes into planning
a well-balanced
plant-based diet
for infants and kids?
For infants, breast milk
is the basis of nutrition,
consisting not only
of critical nutrients
but also
immune-boosting compounds
providing both short
and long-term benefits.
The World Health Organization
recommends breastfeeding
exclusively for the first
six months of life,
and continuing
with the introduction
of complementary foods.
What do we know about
the breast milk composition
of plant-based moms?
Vegetarian and vegan mothers
provide breast milk
with comparable
nutritional value,
with a couple important caveats.
In a direct comparison
of breast milk from omnivore
and vegetarian or vegan moms,
the notable difference
was lower DHA,
the long chain omega-3,
in the milk
from plant-based moms,
due to their avoiding fish,
which is probably a good thing
given how contaminated
the aquatic food chain is.
Thankfully,
ensuring proper supplementation
with pollutant-free sources
can bridge this gap,
just like when there is
proper supplementation
with vitamin B12.
So, provided that women
are eating enough
to cover their
nutritional requirements
and supplementing
with DHA and vitamin B12,
vegan moms can produce
nutritionally similar milk.
But what about
case reports like this
where an infant on a vegan diet
is failing to thrive?
These case reports highlight
the importance of good nutrition
during this period of life
of extremely rapid growth.
By around six months of age,
solid foods
should be introduced.
By that age,
breast milk or formula alone
is not sufficient
to meet the nutritional
needs of infants.
In the first case study,
the infant
was exclusively breastfed
for 10 months,
and then was given
a nutritionally insufficient
rice-based drink.
In the second case report,
the infant did not receive
vitamin D supplementation,
which is recommended for all
children in early life.
Breast milk
should be continued on demand
until the child
is at least one year old.
Formula is also an option
for women who cannot breastfeed.
The VegPlate Junior,
a guide put together
to help with dietary planning
for plant-based kids,
has a helpful visual,
and a more detailed table,
for infants who have started
consuming complementary foods.
And finally,
as we've highlighted before,
raw diets are not appropriate
to meet the nutritional needs
of infants and children.
So, what about nutrient status
and growth in vegan children?
First, caution must be applied
to some populations
defined as vegan,
but who may follow diets
that refuse supplementation.
This is where you can get the
impression from some experts
that vegan diets are
deficient and harmful.
But the current
literature suggests
that plant-based diets
using supplementation
are likely to provide
the recommended amounts
of critical nutrients
to allow normal progression
of height and weight
in children,
and can be beneficial.
There is a reason
to assume that vegans today
may be planning their diets
more adequately
than vegans in the past,
as this way of eating
has been adopted
in the general population,
rather than existing
solely in fringe groups.
And, lucky for us,
there is a new set of studies
aimed at tackling
this very question.
What are the associations
between the modern practice
of vegetarian and vegan diets
in children and
adolescents and health?
Enter the VeChi study,
the Vegetarian and Vegan
Children Study of German kids.
For the one to three-year-olds
eating plant-based
in the VeChi study,
how did their growth compare
to their omnivorous peers?
Overall, vegan, vegetarian,
and omnivorous kids
did not significantly differ.
This is in line
with other studies.
One to three-year-old veg kids
tend to be slightly
smaller and lighter
(but within the normal range)
or have no differences
on average
compared to omni kids.
When the researchers assessed
micronutrients and fatty acids,
they noted special focus
should be paid
to critical nutrients
like vitamin D, iodine,
and DHA for all children,
regardless of their diet,
with extra attention
on riboflavin,
vitamin B12, calcium,
and iron for veg kids.
For a toddler, intake
of riboflavin (vitamin B2)
should be around
500 micrograms per day.
The veg kids were short
by about 40-70 mcg.
Luckily, there are
an abundant variety
of plant-based sources
like nuts, legumes,
and fortified plant-
based milks.
For example,
if your toddler drinks
a cup (240 ml)
of fortified soy milk,
they have already met the
500 mcg recommended intake.
For calcium,
great plant sources include
dark green vegetables,
(like kale, bok choy,
and broccoli),
tofu, almonds,
and calcium-fortified
non-dairy beverages,
like soy milk.
What about the older
VeChi kids, aged 6 to 18?
Although iron intake was low
in the toddler group,
it was higher
in the older veg children,
surpassing the omnivore kids.
There was no elevated risk for
iron deficiency in the veg kids.
The higher intake of iron
in the veg group
may have helped compensate
for the lower bioavailability
of iron from plant foods.
The kids in this group
were also more likely
to take supplements.
Yet, in another recent study,
this one of 5 to 10
year old Polish kids
with adequate
reported iron intakes,
about 8 percent
had mild or moderate
hemoglobin deficiency.
Regardless of diet,
about 3 percent
of one to two-year-olds
in the United States
have iron deficiency anemia,
and given its consequences
for young children,
prevention is a top priority.
For adolescent
and young adult females,
iron deficiency anemia
is around 6 percent,
and menstruation
increases this risk.
It's worth
paying special attention
to include iron-rich foods
at most meals
and, to give a little boost
of iron absorption,
combine with
vitamin C rich foods.
What else did we learn
about the older VeChi kids?
BMI did not differ
across groups.
They were a pretty
healthy bunch.
The plant-based kids had been
veg for four to five years
and most vegan kids
took supplements,
in particular B12,
as they absolutely should.
Hopefully,
the 12 percent who weren't
were eating sufficient amounts
of B12-fortified foods,
as well as vitamin D.
One way the groups did differ
was that the vegan kids
had significantly lower
LDL cholesterol
compared to the vegetarian
and omnivorous kids.
And given that atherosclerosis,
our number one killer,
starts in childhood,
and dietary habits
track into adulthood,
plant-based diets in childhood
could ultimately improve the
cardiometabolic health of adults,
as well as potentially
help prevent obesity,
which often persists
into adulthood.
Visit nutritionfacts.org/audio to see
all of the podcast episodes
with descriptions that include
links to their associated videos.
Sources cited and other details are
available on each video's page.
Information about my books—
How Not to Die, How Not to Diet,
and How Not to Age—
is at nutritionfacts.org/books.
As always, all proceeds from
book sales go to charity.
And sign up for our free newsletter
at nutritionfacts.org/subscribe
to stay updated on the latest
bite-sized videos and articles.
NutritionFacts.org is a
science-based non-profit,
and everything on
the website is free.
There are no ads, no corporate
sponsorships, no kickbacks.
Strictly non-commercial,
not selling anything.
I just put up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.
Thanks for listening.